Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Campaign for Governor of Pennsylvania, 1978; IX.
  - Campaign in Progress, 4.
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence, Individuals, Alphabetical"
        - R, January, 1978- November, 1978 (Box 77, Folder 8)
        - S, January, 1978- November, 1978 (Box 77, Folder 9)
        - T, January, 1978- November, 1978 (Box 77, Folder 10)
        - V, January, 1978- November, 1978 (Box 77, Folder 11)
        - W, X, Y, Z, January, 1978- November, 1978 (Box 77, Folder 12)
      - Thornburgh Campaign and Personal Correspondence, Chron"
        - March 28, 1977-October 4, 1977 (Box 77, Folder 13-16)
        - October 7, 1977-October 28, 1978 (Box 78, Folder 1-6)
        - Personal correspondence, chron file, March 28, 1977-May 26, 1977 (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - Campaign Ephemera
      - Campaign events, ephemera and notes, 1978 (Box 79, Folder 1)
      - Brochures and handouts, Primary, January-May, 1978 (Box 79, Folder 2)
      - Brochures and handouts, General, June-November, 1978 (Box 79, Folder 3)
      - Issue-related brochures and handouts, Primary and General, 1977-1978 (Box 79, Folder 4)
      - Pete Flaherty's political brochures and handouts, 1977-1978 (Box 79, Folder 5)
      - Campaign buttons, stickers, bumper stickers: Primary and General, 1977-1978 (Box 79, Folder 6)
      - Campaign ephemera, 1977-1978 (Box 79, Folder 7)
      - Complete Newspapers for Primary and General "wins", 1977-1978 (Box 79, Folder 8)
  - Issue Research, 5.
    The Issue Research section is arranged into four groups as follows: Gubernatorial Debates; Research System; Issues; and Background Binders. These files consist of materials gathered and generated by campaign staff to provide Thornburgh with the necessary background for debates and to be generally knowledgeable about all issues of concern to Pennsylvanians. Rick Stafford headed this all-important research team.
    The Gubernatorial Debates section is arranged chronologically by each of the two debates. The first occurred on October 10, 1978, and the second on October 25, 1978. These folders contain incredibly detailed materials in preparation for any conceivable question Thornburgh might be asked. They further include the likely responses by Thornburgh's opponent, Pete Flaherty, and even suggestions for Thornburgh's response to them. These files are remarkable and contain an all-inclusive review of all the important campaign issues.
    The Research System files are arranged chronologically. Materials pertain to the complex research system developed and maintained by Rick Stafford's team. Included are filing systems information, memoranda, calendars, correspondence, schedules and notes.
    The Issues files are broken down into thirty-eight topics relevant to Pennsylvania at the time of the '78 campaign. They are arranged alphabetically, from abortion to labor to workmen's compensation. Issue materials include, for example: newspaper clippings, reports, research papers, published materials, and staff notes.
    The Background Binders include a broad range of research on issues, state government departments, and policies. The post-election policy binder was known informally as the "promise binder." This binder referenced all the commitments enumerated during the campaign and which served as a benchmark for future administration accomplishments. For preservation purposes, these materials have been removed from their original binders and placed in acid-free folders. These files present a valuable picture of Pennsylvania preceding Thornburgh's administration.
    - Gubernatorial Debates (2)
      - Debate I: Index and Part I for Debate binder, final form, October 10, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 1)
      - Debate I: Preparation: letters and memos, October 10, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 2)
      - Debate I: Background on media panelists: Karen Stone, Bob Dvorchak, Dave Leherr, October 10, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 3)
      - Debate II: Index and Rick Stafford briefing, formal additions to Debate I binder, October 25, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 4)
      - Debate II: Preparation: letters and memos, October 25, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 5)
      - Debate II: Researchers' analyses of Debate I, October 25, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 6)
      - Debate II: Research update, October 25, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 7)
      - Debate II: Transcript, October 25, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 8)
      - Thornburgh debate binder: Revised for Debate II, October 25, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 9)
      - Flaherty material from Thornburgh's binder, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 10)
      - Documentation on Flaherty's positions, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 11)
      - Memos from Tom Meglen to Rick Stafford regarding Flaherty's positions, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 12)
      - Rick Stafford Strategy Development, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 13)
      - Issue research, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 14)
      - Briefing material prepared by Rick Stafford and researchers, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 15)
    - Research System
      - Correspondence from Rick Stafford requesting research materials, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 16)
      - Preliminary filing system categories, October 1, 1977 and November 21, 1977 (Box 80, Folder 17)
      - Filing system categories and later revisions, December 23, 1977 (Box 80, Folder 18)
      - Subject directory for filing system and dated additions, February 6, 1978 - September 1, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 19)
      - Subject directory and updates: index to Pittsburgh office filing system, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 20)
      - Memoranda and notes from Rick Stafford and Thornburgh to research volunteers regarding background papers, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 21)
      - Rick Stafford's calendar and Thornburgh's annotated long range schedules, 1977 (Box 80, Folder 22)
      - Rick Stafford's agendas, goals, organization, to do lists, drafts and task forces, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 23)
      - Research and development services and products by Rick Stafford: Outlines and formats, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 24)
      - Research Department/Information Service responsibilities memo from Edith Souder, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 25)
      - Research effort: Pittsburgh office guides to issues, assignment logs, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 26)
      - Rick Stafford notes regarding research meetings at Thornburgh's home, June, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 27)
      - Rick Stafford's notes regarding research meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 28)
      - Questions and answers for candidates for primary response book, 1978 (Box 80, Folder 29)
      - Correspondence regarding offers of help with research, 1977-1978 (Box 80, Folder 30)
      - Research memoranda from Bruce Weinrod to Thornburgh, June, 1977 - July, 1977 (Box 81, Folder 1)
      - "A Suggested Research Approach for Richard L. Thornburgh, Republican Candidate for Governor of Pennsylvania," by Michael A. Poling, September 1, 1977 (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - Issues
      - Abortion
        - Correspondence and newsletters, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 3)
        - Material from the Pro-Life Federation, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 4)
      - Aging
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 5)
      - Agriculture
        - Land policy program for Pennsylvania by the Office of State Planning and Development, March, 1978 (Box 81, Folder 6)
        - Memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 7)
      - Arts
        - Correspondence, memoranda, and background research, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 8)
      - Attorney General
        - Articles and editorials, 1977- 1978 (Box 81, Folder 9)
      - Blacks and Minorities
        - Spanish speaking community, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 11)
        - Analysis of Minority Business Program and Department of Commerce from Mark Lewis, September 21, 1978 (Box 81, Folder 12)
        - "People" power and EMAK group material from Morgan Doughton, October, 1978 (Box 81, Folder 13)
        - Memoranda, platform material, statistics, positions, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 14)
        - Campaign meetings, notes, lists, January, 1978-August, 1978 (Box 81, Folder 15)
      - Budgets and Taxes
        - Butera positions, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 16)
        - Budget reform position papers from Raymond Pepe, Walt Plosila, Stumpf, Lopus, September, 1976-June, 1978 (Box 81, Folder 17)
        - Platform proposals; Michel on PA budget; budget priorities, Dempster statistics, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 18)
        - Pennsylvania taxes, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 19)
        - Correspondence, brochures, articles, clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 20)
      - Crime/Corruption
        - Corruption and public officials in Pennsylvania, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 21)
        - "Report to Senator Richard Tilghman, Chairman of Senate Minority Appropriations Committee," revised edition, regarding political corruption in state government, 1974 (Box 81, Folder 22)
        - Background papers regarding crime and public safety, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 23)
        - Articles written by Clifford Karchmer and Marilyn Walsh, 1977 -1978 (Box 81, Folder 24)
        - Pennsylvania Crime Commission: correspondence and notes, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 25)
      - Drugs and Alcohol
        - Correspondence, memoranda, and background research, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 26)
      - Economy
        - Platform outlines of problems and proposals, 1977-1978 (Box 81, Folder 27)
        - Tourism, housing, and neighborhood revitalization, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 1)
        - Steel and coal, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 2)
        - Business climate, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 3)
        - Facts, notes, outlines, problem statements and goals, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 4)
        - Background reports including Pennsylvania Industrial Development Association material from Victor Diehm, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 5)
        - "Growth and Balance: the States' Views," White House Conference on Balanced National Growth and Economic Development, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 6)
        - "The Vital Impact of Travel on Economy of Pennsylvania," by PA Travel Industry Advisory Council, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 7)
      - Education
        - House of Representatives research memos, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 8)
        - "The Financing of Higher Education by Commonwealth" by Mike Myers, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence, clippings, and memos, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 10)
        - Basic and higher education, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 11)
        - Research and surveys, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 12)
        - Platform binder material, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 13)
      - Efficiency in State Government
        - Memos, recommendations, and clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 14)
      - Energy/Public Utilities Commission
        - Staff reports and suggested programs, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 15)
        - Out of office reports and clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 16)
        - Background reports on Governor's Energy Council, Governor's Science Advisory Commission, Pennsylvania State University, League of Women Voters, and 1977 Power Conference, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 17)
      - Environment
        - Staff reports, background reports, and clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 82, Folder 18)
      - Governor's Review of Government Management
        - The Governor's Review, 1972 (Box 82, Folder 19)
        - The Governor's Review (two copies) (annotated), 1975 (Box 82, Folder 20-21)
        - Analyses of Government Review 1972, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 1)
        - Analyses of Government Review 1975, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 2)
      - Gun Control
        - Correspondence, October, 1977-May, 1978 (Box 83, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence, May-November, 1978 (Box 83, Folder 4)
        - Articles and research, 1968-1978 (Box 83, Folder 5)
        - Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 6)
      - Health/Mental Health and Retardation
        - Staff memos and reports (Pennhurst), 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 7)
        - Costs/Medicaid, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 8)
        - Pennsylvania Emergency Health Services Council: Research for questionnaire, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 9)
        - Pennsylvania Psychiatric Society Reports, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 10)
        - Housing and construction, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 11)
        - Human services and welfare, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 12)
      - Jones Commission
        - Report on Governor's Study on Public Employee Relations, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 13)
        - Testimony on Act 195 submitted by the Pennsylvania State Education Association and information on Act 111, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 14)
      - Justice
        - Merit Selection for Judges, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 15)
        - Governor's Justice Commission, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 16)
        - Articles, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 17)
      - Labor
        - Prevailing Wage Tax, Injunctions, and MILRITE, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 18)
        - Pennsylvania State Government Employment, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 19)
        - Department of Labor and Industry research, Thornburgh's notes, and department brochures, 1977 (Box 83, Folder 20)
      - Legislative Reports and Statistics
        - League of Women Voters, Republican Minority (Hager), MacNett letter, June, 1978 (Box 83, Folder 21)
      - Liquor
        - Correspondence and reports, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 22)
      - Multiple Issues
        - Reports, memos, and clippings by Plosila and others, 1977-1978 (Box 83, Folder 23)
      - Pennsylvania Facts and Statistics
        - Research and Memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 1)
      - Pennsylvania Intergovernmental Council
        - Pennsylvania Intergovernmental Council, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 2)
      - Pennsylvania Problems
        - Thornburgh's notes on the Pennsylvania Congressional Delegation Meeting with the President, October, 1977 (Box 84, Folder 3)
        - Pennsylvania Statistical Digests, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 4)
        - Northeast Pennsylvania Issues, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 5)
        - Northwest Pennsylvania Issues, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 6)
        - Southeast Pennsylvania Issues (Bodine Issue Seminars), 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 7)
        - Columns by William Ecenbarger of United Press International (UPI) regarding Pennsylvania problems, 1970-1978 (Box 84, Folder 8-9)
      - Philadelphia
        - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 10)
        - Primary research by Bea Cromwell, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 11)
        - Reports and annotated articles, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 12)
        - Mayor Frank Rizzo, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 13)
        - Staff memos and briefing, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 14)
        - Urban gardening, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 15)
        - Memoranda and reports, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 16)
        - Articles and newspaper clippings (annotated), 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 17)
      - Pittsburgh
        - "A Decade in Retrospect," Pennsylvania Economy League Report, 1977 (Box 84, Folder 18)
      - Platform
        - "Republican White Papers: Briefing Papers on State Government in Pennsylvania," prepared by House Research Staff for Legislative Candidates, June, 1978 (Box 84, Folder 19)
        - Binder research, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 20)
        - Republican platforms: 1962-1974, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 21-22)
        - "Common Sense and Clean Government for a Change in Pennsylvania: a Republican Proposal," by Republican State Committee of PA, 1978 (Box 84, Folder 23)
      - Regulation
        - Insurance, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 24)
        - Public Utilities Commission and Banking, 1977-1978 (Box 84, Folder 25)
      - Public Utilities Commission/Banking
        - Background Research, 1978 (Box 84, Folder 26)
      - Shapp Record
        - Thornburgh/Scranton spending cap plan, 1978 (Box 84, Folder 27)
        - Editorials and responses to Thornburgh/Scranton spending cap, July, 1978-September, 1978 (Box 84, Folder 28)
        - Memos, notes, reports, and information regarding Proposition 13, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 1)
        - Other Pennsylvania proposals, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 2)
        - Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 3)
        - Newsletters, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 4)
        - Reports and annotated articles, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 5)
      - Tax Limitation
        - Allegheny Valley Expressway, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 6)
        - Bridges, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 8)
        - Mass transportation, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 9)
        - Pennsylvania aviation, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 10)
        - PennDOT finances, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 11)
        - "Macing and Extortion in the PA Department of Transportation," prepared by the PA Crime Commission, July, 1978 (Box 85, Folder 12)
        - Rail, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 13)
        - Reports, notes, and articles, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 14-16)
        - Safety, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 17)
        - Turnpike, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 18)
        - Waterways, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 19)
        - Transit research, PAT, SEPTA, and other transit, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 20)
      - Unemployment Compensation
        - Memoranda and articles, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 21)
      - Veterans
        - Background Research, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 22)
      - Women's Issues
        - Memoranda and correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 23)
      - Workmen's Compensation
        - Memoranda and articles, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 24)
      - Youth
        - Correspondence and reports, 1977-1978 (Box 85, Folder 25)
    - Background Binders
      - Index for issue background binders, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 1)
      - Issue background binder no. 1, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - Issue background binder no. 2, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 3)
      - State government binder by department, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 4)
      - State issue background binder, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 5)
      - Staff notes on issue research, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 6)
      - Post-election policy binder, 1978 (Box 86, Folder 7)
      - Republican State Committee platform, 1978 (Box 86, Folder 8)
  - Opposition Research, 6.
    The Opposition Research section is arranged in three groups, as follows: 1978 Gubernatorial and Lieutenant Governor Candidates; Pennsylvania Politicians; and Other Pennsylvania Politicians. Folders are arranged by the name of the politician or candidate. Much of the material here consists of newspaper clippings and the date range is 1977 -1978, though some material dates back to the late 1960s depending on the politician's career. Annotations by Thornburgh are evident throughout these materials.
    The 1978 Gubernatorial and Lieutenant Governor Candidates section is organized by candidate. The bulk of the material pertains to Democrat gubernatorial candidate, Pete Flaherty, Mayor of Pittsburgh from 1970 to 1977. For all candidates the files include newspaper clippings, but also, for example: biographical sketches, campaign literature, reports, Thornburgh staff research, and press releases. In addition to Pete Flaherty, these files include the other major Democrat and Republican figures that ran in the '78 gubernatorial primary. Candidates for Lieutenant Governor include William W. Scranton, III (R) and Robert P. Casey (D).
    A note to the researcher: you will see the name Robert P. Casey twice in this section. In an unusual circumstance, two men with the identical name ran for office in the Primary. The "real" Bob Casey ran for Governor and the other for Lieutenant Governor, capitalizing on the name and reputation of former Auditor General Casey, who opposed Pete Flaherty in the primary, and who years later was a successful candidate for Governor in '86. The Thornburgh campaign successfully identified the '78 Lieutenant Governor candidate, Robert P. Casey, as the "wrong Bob Casey." The endorsement of Thornburgh/Scranton by high school teacher Casey's school newspaper, the Taylor Allderdice "Forward," was a notable campaign event which generated considerable media coverage across the state in the final weeks before the election.
    The Pennsylvania Politicians section include some major Pennsylvania political players, who may have considered running for governor or were thought likely to run, but didn't. The bulk of these materials are newspaper clippings but also included are newsletters and campaign literature.
    The Other Pennsylvania Politicians section is arranged alphabetically. Politicians included here were active figures in Commonwealth politics, whether currently campaigning for public office, or not. The materials collected vary from person to person but primarily consist of newspaper clippings.
    - Candidates for Governor
      - Pete Flaherty (D) Candidate Gubernatorial Race, 1978"
        - The research effort regarding Flaherty's record by Thornburgh staff member Tom Darr and volunteers, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 1)
        - Biographical and personal, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 2)
        - Nancy Flaherty (wife), 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 3)
        - Jim Flaherty (brother), 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 4)
        - City Council Record, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 5)
        - 1969 Mayor Campaign, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 6)
        - Mayor of Pittsburgh, statistics, problems, reports, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 7)
        - Political analysis, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 8)
        - Population figures for the City of Pittsburgh during Flaherty's first term as the Mayor of Pittsburgh, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 9)
        - City of Pittsburgh Bond Ratings, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 10)
        - Pittsburgh economy and business, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 11)
        - Employment in Pittsburgh, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 12)
        - Pittsburgh finances, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 13)
        - City pensions, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 14)
        - Arts, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 15)
        - Blacks, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 16)
        - Education, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 17)
        - Emergency medical services, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 18)
        - Fire insurance rating, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 19)
        - Housing record, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 20)
        - Human services, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 21)
        - Juvenile Justice Center, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 22)
        - Labor, 1977-1978 (Box 87, Folder 23)
        - Senior citizens, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 1)
        - Transportation: Roads and inland waterways, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 2)
        - Pittsburgh bridges, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 3)
        - East Street, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 4)
        - Condition of city parking garages, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 5)
        - Lawsuit with Allegheny Contracting Industries, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 6)
        - Pittsburgh Convention Center, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 7)
        - Opposition to programs and ideas, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 8)
        - U.S. Senate Committee on the Judiciary hearing on nomination of Thornburgh as Assistant Attorney General, June 17, 1975 (Box 88, Folder 9)
        - U.S. Senate Committee on the Judiciary hearing on nomination of Flaherty as Deputy Attorney General, March 22, 1977 (Box 88, Folder 10)
        - Flaherty as attorney general, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 11)
        - Flaherty's addresses and press breakfasts as Deputy Attorney General, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 12)
        - Mayor Flaherty's appointments to City of Pittsburgh positions and lists of his supporters and non-supporters in Pittsburgh government, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 13)
        - Flaherty's relationship with the Democratic Party, 1977-1978 (Box 88, Folder 14)
        - Quotes of Mayor Richard Caliguiri, Democrat, City of Pittsburgh regarding Flaherty, 1973-1978 (Box 88, Folder 15)